大家好 我是Ann-Marie MacDonald
Hi, I'm Ann-Marie MacDonald.
那是我的名字 但是我不会分享
That's my name, but I'm not sharing
我的地址 电话 学校
my address, phone number, the schools I attended
或者我最好的朋友的生日
or my best friends' birthdays.
有的人不明白
People don't seem to understand
个人信息有时候就是隐私
that private data is private for a reason.
你猜我还有啥会压箱底？
You know what else I'd keep to myself?
傻B的照片呀 心底的小妒忌啊
Silly photos, personal grudges
还有那过去的青葱岁月里干的
and anything even remotely embarrassing
都够我发到糗百上的事儿啊
from the distant past.
那些你做傻事的逭
That stupid picture of you
会一直在那
doing that dumb thing is still there
即使你已经老了五岁了
even if you're four years older.
但事实上 近些年来
Thing is, millions are sharing
无数的私人八卦被分享
very personal news nowadays...
我认为是Facebook
I think Facebook brought the end of my marriage
加快了我婚姻的终结
much quicker than it would have been.
警察只是看着屏幕说
The cop just kept looking at the screen and saying,
真不敢相信这家伙这么傻
"I can't believe how stupid this guy is."
本集讲述 facebook的迨
This Doc Zone is all about 'Facebook Follies'.
人类本质上
ANN-MARIE MACDONALD: Human beings,
是种社会型生物
by nature, are social creatures.
我们一个最基本最原始的需求
One of our most basic and primitive needs
就是与他人接触
is to connect with others.
当电报在19世纪被发明后
When the telegraph was invented in the nineteenth century,
它改变了所有事
it changed everything.
接着在通讯方面所有的改革
And all the innovations in communication that followed
都抱着同一原则 让人们聚得更近
served the same purpose: to bring people closer together.
也许有人听说过Facebook
Some of you have probably already heard about Facebook.
我们记录我们的生活 我们和别人互动
We record our lives... we interact with others...
不会有任何疑虑
and without a care in the world
我们在网上分享个人点滴
we share our personal experiences online.
可以说这是以前原始需求
You could say it's a modern version
的现代版本
of the old, primitive need.
我贴吧 我灌水 我围脖 故我在
DR. MARK FEDERMAN: I tweet, I post, I blog, therefore I am.
但是所有的这些分享都冒着一定风险
But all of this sharing comes at a personal risk.
如果你不信 听听奥观海是怎么说的
If you don't believe it, ask the man at the top.
我希望每个人在Facebook发啥玩意儿
PRESIDENT OBAMA: I want everybody here to be careful about
都长点心吧
what you post on Facebook.
我一直
GRAHAM CLULEY: I remember
相信达尔文效应 就是
believing in the early days that Darwin would
人会从过错中学习
have an effect. People would learn from their
现在恐怕并不是这样
past mistakes. And I'm afraid it's not happening.
人类在电脑屏幕前仍然是穴居生物
People are basically still cave men in front of their
他们是尼安德特人(是一种在大约12万到3万年前冰河时期本来居住在欧洲及西亚的人种)
computer keyboards. They're Neanderthals.
不管是否穴居 世界上绝对没有任何事
Cavemen or not, nothing in the world, absolutely nothing,
像Facebook一样做为社交媒体吸引如此多人
is attracting as many users of social media as Facebook.
Facebook是一个
GREY BLOKE: Facebook is a
大型多人在线角色扮演游戏
massively multiplayer on-line role-playing
游戏目标就是攒"朋友"
game in which the objective is to collect "Friends".
你丫如果不上Facebook
GRAHAM CLULEY: You're not anyone on the Internet if you're not
在网络世界，你就是个路人
on Facebook.
简单说 社交媒体改变了人类互动的方式
Simply put, social media is changing the way
在许多情况下 前路崎岖
people interact. In many cases, it's a bumpy ride,
与那些甚至没见过的人
all that personal information being shared,
分享的所有私人信息
with people we've never even met, with consequences
产生的结果无法预测
down the road that are impossible to predict.
是不是很疯狂 好吧 问问孩子们
How crazy is this, really? Well, just ask the kids.
Facebook用来分享要发生的事
Facebook is being used to share information about
婚礼 聚会 音乐会
upcoming events: weddings, gatherings, concerts and
尤其是派对
especially parties.
最近一个德国的女孩使用Facebook
Recently, a girl in Germany used Facebook
来告诉朋友们自己要16岁了
to let her friends know she was turning 16.
她忘了检查隐私设置
She forgot to check the privacy settings...
派对邀请在Facebook传给了每个人
and the party invitation went out to everyone on Facebook.
牛B!
Woops.
数千浮躁的青少年聚在一块儿瞎得瑟
Thousands of boisterous teenagers showed up.
这个家庭派对取消的公告
Desperate public announcements by the family that
没起到任何作用
the party was cancelled made no difference.
Facebook已经在聚集人们方面
Facebook had worked it's particular magic in
散发出了刘谦般的魔力
bringing people together.
在Facebook上 她写着 现在这里正有一个派对
From Facebook. She texted that there's a party right now here,
我只是打酱油的
but I don't get in.
Thessa!姐们儿挺你!!!!
Thessa! Wooooooo!!!!
这个16岁的小寿星 Thessa 已经见不着人了
The birthday girl, 16 yr old Thessa, was nowhere to be seen.
她早在那一天之前逃到
She had fled to her grandparents place earlier
祖父母家了
in the day.
(人群喊)Thessa!!
CROWD Thessa!!
Thessa生日快乐
Happy Birthday dear Thessa...
在Facebook上一个无心的点击
One careless click on Facebook.
一个16岁孩子的小过错
A momentary lapse by a sixteen year old ...
成就了Facebook终身污名
a lifetime of Facebook notoriety.
Thessa证明了 在Facebook上
Thessa found out FAST what the consequences of
星星之错可以燎原
a Facebook mistake can be.
但并不是总这么快见效
But It doesn't always play out this way.
有时候会过很久哦～～
Sometimes... it can take years.
卑斯省因它政治上的火药味浓漫而著名
British Columbia is known for its sometimes scrappy
看看其中的一个例子
provincial politics. This is one of its many ridings:
温哥华福湾 一个住宅和商业的混合区
Vancouver False Creek. A mix of residential and commercial.
2009年的竞选是自由党一边儿倒
In 2009, this was a Liberal-held riding.
省新民主党想逆袭
The provincial NDP wanted to change that,
他们尝试着
and they thought they might with a fresh candidate,
推选一个政治新人为候选人
someone completely new to politics. Their candidate:
这个年轻的候选人Ray Lam
Ray Lam, younger than your average politician,
引进了一个新颖的方法
and ready for a new way of doing things.
我看到了Facebook和Twitter的潜力
I saw the potential of Facebook and Twitter and I tried to
我尝试用它们与我的粉丝交流
use that to communicate with my constituents.
在Ray的竞选中 Facebook确实起到了作用
Facebook did play a part in Ray's campaign,
但与他的想法背道而驰
but not at all in the way he imagined it would.
正在是关键时刻 他的政治生涯
Just as it was getting off the ground, his political career
突然走向终结
came to a sudden and spectacular end.
这归功于在Facebook上的一些老照片
All thanks to some old photos found on Facebook,
它们出现在对手――自由党控制的媒体上
and leaked to the media by his Liberal opponent.
那是些高中照片
They were high school photos.
在当时无可指摘
In that context it's fairly innocuous. But ah, the way that,
但竞选时被挖了出来
the context that it was put in during the campaign
它们产生了轰动
made it a lot more volatile than it actually was.
在一张照片上 我和我的一个朋友热舞
In one photo I'm dancing with a friend of mine
而我的手放在她的乳房上 另一张照片上
and my hand is on her breast. In another photo um,
额 我两个朋友正在看我的内裤
I have two friends that are looking at my underwear.
这些多年前的照片
The pictures, taken years before, and mostly forgotten,
本已尘封在Facebook的一个角落里
were preserved in a quiet corner of Facebook.
这些新闻其实并不是新民主党的策划
The news wasn't covering NDP policy decisions anymore,
或阴谋
or the NDP platform.
他们谈论着Facebook上的照片
They were talking about these Facebook pictures.
我认为这有欠考虑
I thought they showed a lack of judgment.
那确实是他的过去
It's his age, you know, we all recognize that.
但当你成为政治人物或者
But when you're in politics and you're going to be
公众人物 就有点不合时宜了
a public figure, it's important that you recognize that.
Ray决定停止并退出竞选
Ray took the decision to step down and quit the race,
一段政治生涯被粉碎了
a political career dashed to pieces
只因为几张高中恶搞照片
by some random high school photos.
Ray错过了进入政坛的机会
For Ray, it's a lost opportunity,
他简直比窦娥还冤呐...
and more than a little unfair.
Clive Thompson 是个自由撰稿的新闻工作者
Clive Thompson is a freelance journalist.
他的关注点就是因特网
His expertise is the internet, and how it's changing
和它怎样改变我们记录生活的方式
the way our lives are being recorded.
一直以来 我们总会让我们做过的
You know, for generations we've been able to move on from
坏事或傻事随风而逝
bad or dumb things we've done.
但在Facebook中 公众遗忘却有点难了
But in Facebook, 'social forgetting' is a lot harder.
因为那些做傻事的照片一直在那
Because that photo of that dumb thing you did is still there.
它并不会消失
It doesn't degrade.
让人担忧的就是Facebook
So the fear is that Facebook makes 'social forgetting'
会使公众遗忘变得困难甚至不可能
difficult or impossible. It makes it harder to move on
它使你更难以摆脱过去 继续生活
from things you did in the past.
当我回想我过去的经历
When you look at what I've done and what I've been through
从高中开始 那些教育经历 工作经验
since high school, the education, the work experience,
社团活动 这些
experience in the community, that far outweighs
远比那些照片更重要
what I would have, or could have done when I was in high school.
Ray的故事拷问我们:在未来的日子里
Ray's story raises the question: in future years, who
谁能足够清白地从政
will be squeaky-clean enough to run for political office?
每天总有一些如定时炸弹般的照片和围脖
Every day literally millions of potentially damaging photos
被世界上的有心人看到并记住
and tweets are uploaded for the world to see and remember.
2011年4月威廉王子和凯特的世纪婚礼
The Royal Wedding of William and Kate, April 2011.
场面宏大，规格很高
A ceremonial occasion if ever there was one.
对于英国军队各军团来说
And a prestigious moment for the various regiments in
这也是一个荣耀时刻
Britain's armed forces.
他们之中装饰最华丽的就是英格兰卫队
Amongst them... the much-decorated Scots Guards.
被挑选在这样一个日子里值勤
Being selected for active duty on a day like this
是件很值得吹嘘的事
is a big deal.
一个近卫兵就没这福气了
One guardsman who didn't make the cut,
他就是18岁的Cameron Reilly
18 year-old Cameron Reilly.
还得从他在Facebook页面的更新说起
And all because of a posting he put on his Facebook page.
在一个脑残的分享中
In a spectacular display of bad judgment,
Reilly竟然毫不避讳地称呼这位新娘是
for all the world to see, Reilly called the bride-to-be
一头傲慢的奶牛
a "Stuck up cow".
意犹未尽 他还添上"艳丽婊子"
For good measure, he threw in "Posh bitch", and
谁tmd在乎她呀
"Who really gives a f××× about her?"
因为他的轻率
For this indiscretion, Reilly was removed
Reily与皇家婚礼彻底绝缘了
from Royal Wedding duty.
这件事或许会继续困扰
It's a story that will likely
他的整个军旅生涯
haunt his entire military career.
谁知道呢
Or what's left of it.
还有一个英国人 一直耿耿于怀于
Another Briton, who probably wishes
自己一次的口直心快
he had kept his thoughts
他就是26岁的会计师Paul Chambers
to himself, is 26 year-old accountant Paul Chambers.
Chambers买了张机票
Chambers had bought a ticket to fly from a small regional
准备去贝尔法斯特看望女友
airport to Belfast, to visit his girlfriend.
起飞的9天前
Nine days before he was due to fly,
机场因为暴风雪停飞了
the airport was shut down by a snowstorm.
Chambers决定给机场一些礼貌的提醒
Chambers decided to send the airport a friendly warning
他在自己的Twitter账号里写道
via his Twitter account:
浑蛋 Robin Hood机场关闭了
Crap！Robin Hood Airport closed.
给你们一个星期的时间拉屎
You've got a week and a bit to get your shit together,
否则我就把机场炸出翔来
otherwise i'm blowing the airport sky high
真是一个馊主意
Bad idea Mr. Chambers.
刚好该机场的网络联接着推特
Because of the public network used to carry the tweet,
机场职工被这个警告吓尿了
airport staff were alerted to it.
他们傻兮兮地没看出这是个玩笑
And they failed to see the joke.
Chambers非常荣幸得成为英国第一个
Chambers holds the distinction of being the first person
根据反恐法被起诉的人
in the UK to be prosecuted under the Terrorism Act
他在Twitter上的更新便成了证据
for remarks made on Twitter.
因为这个闹剧 他财务经理的职位被炒了鱿鱼
Because of all the fuss, he was fired from his job as a
他到底是怎么想的?
financial manager. So, what was he thinking?
看着这家伙做的
CLIVE THOMPSON: You look at the
你会不会稍稍摇头
actions of this guy and you sort of shake your
你是不是有时候也像他一样二
head, and you're like 'are you some sort of an idiot?'
说句公道话 他以为自己在这样一个场合中闲谈
But then, on the one hand it's like, well, he's just in this
这个场合就是如果说点什么
collision point in society between a world where if I say
只有这个房间里的人能听到
something, only the people in my room are going to hear it.
但是如果在网上说点什么 那每个人都能听到了
And where if I say something on-line, everyone's going to
他二就二在没分清楚这点
hear it. And he hasn't quite got his mind around that yet.
最后 Chambers被判应缴罚款
In the end, the judge fined Chambers the equivalent of
折合美元1500刀
fifteen hundred dollars,
并进入该机场黑名单 一辈子
And he was banned from the airport - for life.
Chambers死不悔改 针对自己的判决
Unrepentant, Chambers responded to his conviction
在另一条说说里他写道
in yet another tweet.
我非常感谢他们做出的杰出贡献
i'd like to thank the crown for their level best efforts
我操蛋的一生竟能荣获如此殊荣 我爱大英帝国
in f***ing up the life of an ordinary citizen.i love Britain
谁会认为一个慈善洗车场
And who would have thought a charity car wash could
会引来麻烦呢
cause a problem?
但是 它确实在卡罗莱纳州发生了
Well, it did in South Carolina last year,
它发生在一个小镇警察局
at a small town police department.
一个正在执勤的警员停下自己的警车
An officer, on duty, stopped by to have his police car washed
让一比基尼辣妹洗车
by women wearing bikinis.
不错 有人拍下了照片
Inevitably, someone took photos.
然后这些照片出现在Facebook上
And the pictures landed on Facebook.
当地警察局长并不觉得这事很逗
The local police chief was not amused.
他认为这违背了警车使用法规
He said it was a violation of the rules governing the use
严重损害了警局的形象
of police vehicles. It reflected badly on the force.
于是该问题警员被辞退了
The officer in question was fired.
它的模式是这样:有人上传照片
You see how this works? Someone posts a picture,
有人就遭遇麻烦
big problem for someone else.
糗照门不仅仅使美国小镇陷入麻烦
Inappropriate photos don't just trouble small town America,
首都也不例外
it happens in the nation's capital too,
那些被认为会理性对待推特的人
affecting people who you might think would be more savvy
可能也会出人意料
with their tweets.
结果便出现了这种不必要的案例
Well it turns out... that's not necessarily the case.
看看美国国会议员Anthony Weiner吧
Enter US Congressman Anthony Weiner.
他千辛万苦分享到推特上的
He found out, the hardest way possible,
这张照片 这张...特写
that tweeting this picture of his..... package,
实在是太闷骚了
was a colossal blunder.
我为自己的脑残犯二行为感到羞愧
I'm deeply ashamed of my terrible judgment and actions.
不可避免地 这位国会议员被迫炒了自己鱿鱼
Inevitably, the congressman was forced to resign.
每个人都摇着头问
And everywhere people shook their heads and asked:
他到底有没有脑子
"What was he thinking?"
事实上 许多人还真不用脑子
The fact is, many people appear not to think before they
就在推特或Facebook上更新
send out a Tweet, or post something on Facebook.
那就让暴风雨来得更猛烈些吧
They are taking a huge risk.
因为你永远不会真正明白谁才是你的好基友
Because, you never really know who your friends are.
这事英国一个平静乡村的中心地带
Here in the peaceful heart of the English countryside,
一场战役正在进行
there's a battle going on.
这是一场关于个人隐私和信息的全球战争
It's a global war over privacy and personal information.
在这些定制的互联设施中
Inside this custom-built state-of-the-art facility,
一个名为SOPHOS的公司拦截各种计算机病毒
a company called SOPHOS intercepts computer viruses
这家公司的工作就是
of all kinds. The company's job is to
保护一些世界上最大的企业和
protect some of the world's largest corporations and
政府部门免受网络攻击
government departments against cyber-attack.
在Sophos 他们每天都见到有人因
Everyday, at Sophos , they see the unhappy results of
对私人资料粗心大意而造成不愉快
people being careless with personal data.
Graham Cluley是这家公司
Graham Cluley is one of the company's
的一个高级技术顾问
senior technology consultants.
他的一部分工作就是监控Facebook
Part of his job is to keep a close eye on Facebook.
很多人都没理解
while most people don't understand on Facebook.
Facebook的开发是商业行为 而不是情感宣泄
it's not being done for love. It's a business.
它甚至并不完全免费
And it's not even free.
你或许会想 哼 反正我也不付钱
You may think well, I'm not paying for this. Well,
但是你支付的是你的个人资料
you are paying for it. You're paying for it with your data.
你正在泄露的个人信息
You're giving away personal information which is a
正是Facebook可以用来赚钱的商品
commodity to Facebook which they can sell onto others.
所以你是产品 而Facebook负责销售
So you actually are the product which Facebook is selling.
你就是产品 包括你的生日信息
You - the product. Along with your date of birth,
你的喜好 你的邮箱地址
your likes and dislikes, your email address,
你的兴趣爱好
your interests and hobbies.
Sophos怀疑 Facebook用户是不是通常
SOPHOS suspected that as a rule, Facebook users are
对泄露个人信息这方面太不上心了
far too loose about giving away their personal data.
为了证明 他们用一只塑料青蛙的头像
To prove it, they created a Facebook page for a small
创建一个Facebook主页 邀请200名陌生人
plastic frog, and invited 200 complete strangers to become
加为Facebook好友
Facebook friends.
几乎有一半测试者分享了自己的个人信息
Almost half the sample jumped at the chance to share their
给这只叫Freddie的青蛙
personal information with Freddie the Frog.
他们的姓名 好友名单
Their full name, list of friends,
教育经历 都不断被分享
educational information... on and on they went.
然而这就是问题所在
GRAHAM CLULEY: There's a general problem here,
人们看起来不明白
though, that people don't
在某些方面私人信息
seem to understand that your private data is private
就是隐私
for a reason.
一旦出现在网上 你就永远不能将它收回
Once it's on the Internet, you can't ever drag it back.
它就永远在那里 天长地久
It's out there forever more, and that's it.
而你失去了它
You've lost it.
就是说在未来其他人能盗取它
It means someone else can steal it in future.
现在无时不刻不在发生着
It happens all the time.
电脑黑客和网络骗子
Computer hackers and fraudsters stealing
盗取其他人的Id来盈利
other people's identities, to make money.
在社交媒体上 这类事更数不胜数
And more and more, it's happening on social media.
在人类历史上
CLIVE THOMPSON: It's a truth of human history that
每当一项新技术出现 最早的开发人里
whenever a new technology comes along, one of the first people
总有一个是罪犯
who are going to exploit it are criminals.
因为它给他们提供了一中新方法
Because it gives them a new way to reach into people's lives
去欺骗和愚弄人们  你应该见过电邮类犯罪
to gull them, to dupe them ah, and you saw that with e-mail,
比如邮箱欺诈之类的
you know, like scam e-mail things,
现在Facebook也一样
now we're seeing it with Facebook.
Brian Rutberg就曾遭遇这种经历
Brian Rutberg knows a thing or two about internet scams.
他曾在微软做公关主管很多年
For years, he worked at Microsoft as a
2009年 他的Facebook页面
communications director. In 2009, his Facebook page
被一个职业黑客盗取
was taken over by a professional hacker.
我女儿正在沙发上写作业
My daughter was doing homework on the couch.
她写完作业 查看Facebook上的动态
She finished her homework, checked her Facebook page
看见我的状态更新为
and saw that my status had updated to:
Bryan Rutberg迫切需要帮助
'Bryan Rutberg is in urgent need of help'.
所以她回头喊 出什么事了吗?
So she yelled back, is everything okay?
还好 没什么事啊
"Yeah, everything's just fine."
当然 事儿可不少
Of course ... everything wasn't fine.
黑客有条不紊地
The hacker was methodically contacting
接触Rutberg所有的Facebook好友
all of Rutberg's Facebook friends,
告诉他们自己有大麻烦
telling them that he was in big trouble.
我在伦敦有生命危险
BRYAN RUTBERG: I've been held
Sharon和孩子们与我在一起
up at gunpoint in London. I'm here with Sharon
他们当然知道我妻子的名字
and the kids. Of course they knewy wife's name because
因为她也是我的Facebook好友
she was a friend of mine on Facebook.
他们也能浏览我的照片 我感到很糟糕
They could see my pictures. I felt terrible about this
因为这个黑客尝试着
because I knew that whoever this was who had taken over my page
和我所有的朋友接触
was going to be trying to reach out to all my friends.
这让我很头疼
That was going to be a headache for me, and I felt terrible
我对自己朋友被欺骗一筹莫展
for what it was going to do to my friends.
这名黑客坚持着
The hacker on Rutberg's page was persistent.
不久他就找到一个人
Before long, he found someone willing to send money to a
愿意汇钱帮助Facebook好友的人
Facebook friend-in-need.
Rutberg的老朋友Benny出现
Rutberg's long-time friend Benny stepped up.
最终
BRYAN RUTBERG: In the end,
他通过西联分两次
he sent over twelve hundred dollars in two separate
共汇了1200刀
payments through Western Union.
一个英国人自称是我
And someone in the UK went to the Western Union office
到西联营业处取走了它们
and picked it up, claiming to be me.
这种"亟需帮助"诈骗早在伊丽莎白一世统治时
This "Cry-for-help" Scam has its origins centuries ago
就已经出现
in the reign of Elizabeth the First.
那时候 受害者被骗交付现金
Back then, the victims were conned into handing over money
来帮助据说是被关押西班牙地下室的英国人
to help release Englishmen supposedly locked up
重获自由
in Spanish dungeons.
它被称为 西班牙囚徒骗局
It's known as "The Spanish Prisoner" Scam...
400年后 高科技晚辈们
and four hundred years later, high-tech descendants have
在Facebook上推陈出新
found their way onto Facebook.
Facebook是
GRAHAM CLULEY: Facebook is
增速最快的以互联网为依托的
the fastest growing hotbed of computer crime
计算机犯罪温床
that exists on the Internet.
Facebook上的犯罪活动 像垃圾邮件 流氓程式等
There's more crime, spam, scams, malware, taking place
比其他地方更多
on Facebook than anywhere else.
如果你想参观世界计算机犯罪集中营
If you want to go into the cyber crime hub of the world
现在就来Facebook吧
right now, it's Facebook.
让我们看一下个例子 小偷的自拍
When we come back... the face of crime on Facebook...
在Facebook上公布于众
for all the world to see.
我们甚至
GRAHAM CLULEY: We've even
看到歹徒和窃贼发布
seen criminals and burglars post pictures of
在犯罪现场炫耀赃物的照片
themselves at a burglary scene with the money in their hands.
甚至分享到Facebook上
And posted it up on Facebook.
有一个安静的住宅区
A quiet residential neighbourhood of
座落在华盛顿特区
Washington, D.C.
住着报纸编辑Marc Fisher和他的儿子Aaron
This is newspaper editor Marc Fisher and his son Aaron,
他们都是Facebook用户 还互相加了好友
both Facebook users. Facebook friends, in fact.
不久前 在他们私人住宅里
Not long ago, in the sanctity of their own home,
他们亲自体验了
they experienced first-hand just how bizarre the
Facebook这个新世界的奇特之处
new world of Facebook can be.
那得从星期五下午说起
It started on a Friday afternoon.
有人从后门闯入了他们的房间
Someone broke into their house, through the back door.
窃贼在房间里搜寻着
The burglar worked his way through the rooms,
顺走任何看上眼的东西
taking anything that caught his eye....
包括一些现金和Aaron的手提
including some cash... and Aaron's laptop.
那件才从梅西百货买的
to a brand new winter coat
崭新的冬大衣也没放过
that had just been delivered from Macy's.
当Aaron回家后小偷已经逃之夭夭了
The thief was long gone before Aaron got home from school,
发现被窃后 他电邮了父母
realized things were missing, and emailed his parents.
我们收到邮件
First thing we knew we got an email
第一眼就看到标题行的"Help"
and the subject line was "Help!"
Fishers夫妇立刻报警并赶回家
The Fishers immediately called the cops and rushed home,
到家的时候警察还没到
arriving just before the officers did.
警察马上将我们与房子隔离
The police threw us out of the house in a matter of seconds
他们好检查房子里是否还有人躲藏
so they could search the house, see if anyone was still here.
没什么进展 这是一个惯偷
So far, a routine burglary.
但接着离奇的事发生了
But then things took a strange twist.
我收到朋友的一条信息 他说
I got a text message from a friend who said,
哇 你Facebook页面上的照片是神马
"Whoa, what's that picture on your Facebook page?"
我跑上楼去用爸爸没被偷走的台式电脑
I ran upstairs to my Dad's desktop computer, which was
登录Facebook 明白无误地看到
still there, I go onto Facebook and sure enough,
在Facebook相册里有一张照片
there's a picture on my Facebook wall.
当窃贼拿着Aaron的手提离开房子时
Before he had left the house with Aaron's laptop, the
他用手提上的摄像头给自己拍了张照片
burglar had taken a picture of himself using the laptop
还上传到了Aaron的主页上
camera. And he actually posted it on Aaron's Facebook page
还所有人可见
for the world to see.
我马上把一个警官叫到
Instantly it all came together, and I called one of the
楼上的房间里
police officers into my office upstairs and ah, showed him
给他看照片 告诉他 那就是我们的梁上君子
the photo and said, 'that's your guy.'
他穿着一件大外套 脸上表情似乎在傻笑
He's wearing a big coat, and he kind of has a smirk on his face,
他的另一只手冲着钞票
and he's pointing to the cash um, with his other hand.
警察只是看着屏幕说
The cop just kept looking at the screen and saying,
真不敢相信这家伙这么傻
"I can't believe how stupid this guy is."
由于他不但掌握了Aaron的Facebook账户
...because not only did he take control of Aaron's Facebook
还把Aaron的账户注销并登录了自己的
account, but he then signed off Aaron's Facebook and signed onto
用的还是同一台电脑
his own account using the same computer,
即那台被偷的电脑
the same stolen computer.
警察通过他的Facebook账户追查到他
Police were able to trace the burglar through his
他最终被捕并送入法院
Facebook account, and he was arrested and charged.
19岁Rodney King对罪状供认不讳
Nineteen year old Rodney King pleaded guilty,
现正在监狱服刑
and is now serving time in prison. It's not known
这位仁兄是否还使用Facebook不得而知
whether he still keeps up his Facebook page.
我们人类的一个劣根性就是有时会无法判断
One of the problems we humans have is that we're often kind of
自己正在做的事是不是脑残
bad at judging whether or not something we're doing is,
或者一年以后看起来是不是脑残
is stupid or not, or is going to look stupid a year from now
有时候你变化特别大
you know. Because like, particularly if you're young,
由于是当你很年轻的时候
you know, like your, your identity changes very quickly
一个人19岁的时候
And the person you are at like 19, might be completely
可能与两年后完全不一样
different from the person you are two years later.
Facebook上的一大挑战就是
One of the challenges Facebook has is that you know,
我们可能发一张觉得确实有趣的照片
we might put up a photo thinking this is really funny,
而当两年后找工作的时候
and then two years later you're looking for a job
你的面试官就会针对它进行发问
and your potential boss is querying this.
记录你糗事的照片会一直在那
That stupid picture of you doing that dumb thing, is still there
似乎在暗示这事还刚做不久
exactly as it was, you know, the day you did it,
即使已经过去了四年
even if you're four years older.
再来看看 斯坦利杯决赛后
Case in point: the riots in Vancouver after the
一场发生在温哥华的骚乱
Stanley Cup Final.
相继有几百人摆姿势拍照和摄影
Literally hundreds of people posed for pictures and videos,
大多数图像都发到推特和Facebook上
many of the images destined for Facebook and YouTube.
似乎此刻最重要的就是那些照片
It was as if all that mattered were the pictures themselves,
而接下来会有什么后果完全不被考虑
not the consequences sometime down the road.
好像每件事都只在当时当地有效
Everything was happening right then, right there,
过去了就过去了
and nowhere else.
但在社交媒体的时代 显然并非如此
Which, in the age of social media, is clearly not the case.
Mark Federman教授在社交媒体
Dr. Mark Federman is an educator and an expert in
如何改变人们交流方式上很有研究
the way new media is changing the way people connect.
当今社会已经明显不同于
The world is today a different place than the world in which
我们这代人赖以长大的社会了
many of us grew up.
我们在社会上的经验似乎很生疏了
Our experience of the world seems so strange.
很多人做着一些看起来不合时宜的事
There are people doing things that seem inappropriate.
旧的规则似乎不再适用 这导致我们感到很迷惑
Old rules don't seem to apply, and we're really confused and
也很矛盾 因为我们生活在
conflicted about it, because we're living through a time of
一个快速更迭的时代
massive transformation, the likes of which we haven't seen
与16世纪中期一样一样的
since the middle of the 16th Century.
温哥华那晚发生的事
A rich stream of the sights and sounds of that evening in
立刻在网上引起了大规模的争论
Vancouver was available instantly, on-line.
社交媒体建立起来的全球社交链
The global connection that social media creates is
让任何事无所遁形且永垂不朽
all-seeing and never forgets.
所有人都是有内在联系的
We are all connected. We all do things that affect one another.
我们做的每件事都会影响另一个人
We all have an effect on people that we don't even know
世界某角落的某人说不定就被我们影响着
in far places around the world. So it is important, I think, for
应该意识到 此之因 彼之果
all of us to realize that what I do here affects you there,
因为没有彼 只有此
because there is no 'there'. There's only 'here'.
在网上 天涯海角即为此地
And on-line 'everywhere' is here.
天长地久即为此时
And 'right now' can be forever.
紧跟着温哥华的这场骚乱
Immediately following the Vancouver riots a new Facebook
出现了一个Facebook主页
page sprang up it's purpose was to identify rioters from the
专门人肉照片里的人 并公开谴责他们
available pictures, to name them and publicly shame them.
有的人称之为网络暴民
Some people called it an "On-line lynch mob".
该站点里全是这类照片
Regardless, the site is full of pictures of people
他们拍照时从没想到
doing things they never imagined would be seen
所有人都会看到它们
all over the world.
在现实生活中你的所作所为
And in real life if you say something, if you do something,
一般只有你旁边的人会知道
the people in your immediate vicinity will know about it,
然而在Facebook上
but really no one else, most of the time. Whereas on Facebook,
你的所作所为
if you say something or do something, the people that
会马上被关注你的人发现
follow you will discover that
一些你不曾留心的人正关注着你
and some of the people you forgot were following you,
你一两年前的朋友看到后
that you friended a year or two ago will see it,
他们朋友的朋友就有可能也看到
potentially, and maybe their friends of friends will see it
他们或许会把这些剪贴到
and maybe someone will cut and paste it and send it somewhere
一些令人意想不到的地方
that you would never have dreamed of. And that is
这也是许多人仍然不用Facebook的原因
what a lot of people still don't get about Facebook.
一些这样的照片会带来误解
And pictures like this can be misleading.
一些打酱油的便会被认为是真正的骚乱者
Who is actually rioting? And who isn't?
在Facebook上看到的
What we think we see in a Facebook post may not be
有可能并不是真相
what is actually going on.
从蒙特利尔到其东部的小镇
It's a little more than an hour's drive from Montreal
只要一个小时多一点
to get to the Eastern Townships.
这里是Cowansville 一场蚍蜉与大树的较量
Here in Cowansville there's a David-versus-Goliath struggle
正在进行
being played out.
这是Nathalie Blanchard和她的律师Tom Lavin
Meet Nathalie Blanchard, and her lawyer Tom Lavin.
在当地法院 他们正准备
At the local courthouse, they are preparing to do battle
与当地最大的保险公司之一对簿公堂
with one of North America's largest insurance companies.
2009年Nathalie被诊断出患有忧郁症
In 2009, Nathalie was diagnosed with clinical depression.
她所在的Manulife保险公司
Her employer's insurance company, Manulife, provided
为她提供保险和福利
coverage and benefits as Nathalie struggled to recover.
医生说 出去 对你来说
My doctor said to me, "Go out, it's very important for you
出去见见人 见见朋友非常重要
to go out and see people, see your friends,
去餐厅 去酒吧 去你想去的任何地方
go in restaurant, go in bar, go everywhere you want.
作为治疗的一部分 医生不但建议她和朋友
As part of her treatment, as well as going out with friends
出去走走 还鼓励她旅行
the doctor also advised that Nathalie go on a trip.
于是 她和老妈去了佛罗里达州
So, she went to Florida with her mother.
上传了一些照片到Facebook上
And she put some photos up on Facebook.
然后 Manulife公司看到了照片
Somehow, Manulife became aware of the pictures,
没给出其他原因就打电话通知
made a judgment call, and without giving her any other
他们中断了Nathalie的福利
reason - they cut off Nathalie's benefits.
问题不在于能否使用Facebook
The issue is not whether or not they can use what is available
而在于怎么使用它
to them on Facebook, it's how they use it.
引起问题的原因是
That is the problem. It's the misinterpretation of
Facebook上的东西被曲解了
what is on Facebook.
我们做个假设
DR. MARK FEDERMAN: If, hypothetically,
如果有一个人
you had a person who was diagnosed and
患上了忧郁症
suffering from clinical depression,
这是个毁灭性的疾病啊 这个人的家人
which is a devastating disease, and the person's family takes
为了给他换个环境而带他去渡假
them away on a vacation just as a change of scenery,
然后这个人上传了他们的一些照片
the person posts a picture of themselves,
难道调查员就能说
if that investigator then says, "Aha, the person has
"嘿 这人是在欺诈 中断他们的福利"吗？
perpetrated fraud, cut off their benefits",
大错特错
that fundamentally is wrong.
我上传照片
NATHALIE BLANCHARD: When I
只是为了掩饰自己的忧郁症
put the picture on Facebook, it was only to hide
并没有想过谁会看这些照片
the depression. And I didn't think about who's going to see
我只是想让大家相信
the picture. I just want to make people believe that
我一切都好
everything is okay in my life.
由于被中断了福利 Nathalie的信用等级没了
Cut off from her benefits, Nathalie lost her credit rating
最终她的房子也泡汤了
and eventually, her house.
有一部经典卡通片里有这样一个场景
You know the old ah, the old cartoon that we see of a guy
一个被认为有残疾的人
that's supposed to be off on disability with ah,
就是一个可能背部或其他地方有毛病的人
with a broken back or something like that, and he's,
他居然在锄草 而侦探拿着相机躲在篱笆下
he's mowing his lawn, and the detective is underneath the
我们现在不这样干
hedge with a camera, we don't have that anymore.
现在我们用Facebook 它有一样的效果
Now we have Facebook, which is the same thing.
不仅一样 保险公司使用起来
Exactly the same thing, except it's more efficient
甚至更有效
for the insurance companies to use.
任何人都不能
DR. MARK FEDERMAN: No one
作出医疗鉴定
can make a medical assessment, can make a
或心理和精神诊断 而依据仅仅是
psychological or psychiatric judgment on the basis of
Facebook上一些脱离环境的照片
an out-of-context picture posted on Facebook.
Nathalie的案例将于2012年前宣判
Nathalie's case goes before a judge in 2012.
全世界的保险调查员 隐私专家
Insurance investigators, privacy experts and
和劳动律师等都会
labour lawyers, literally all over the world, will be
关注此事的动态
glued to the case.
让我们看下一个
When we come back...
年轻的爱
young love.
两个完全陌生的人
Two complete strangers and how a late night
怎样被一次Facebook夜聊彻底改变
Facebook chat changed everything.
一直说Facebook
We keep hearing that Facebook is all about
促进交流
making connections.
那么就来看看一段御宅族的爱情故事
So, how about a love story, unfolding inside this house
这是佛罗里达州罗德尔堡附近
near Fort Lauderdale, Florida.
这是两个很有缘分的年轻人
Meet two young people with a lot in common,
猜猜他们有什么是一样的
including something you might not expect.
我叫Kelly Hildebrandt
My name is Kelly Hildebrandt.
我也叫Kelly Hildebrandt
K-E-L-L-Y
Alternating: K-E-L-L-Y
Hildebrandt
Hildebrandt.
H-I-L-D-E-B-R-A-N-D-T
Alternating: H-I-L-D-E-B-R-A-N-D-T.
你能吃几个煎饼
How many pancakes do you want?
两个Kelly Hildebrandt
For Kelly Hildebrandt and Kelly Hildebrandt,
的缘分开始于Facebook
life together began on Facebook.
一天晚上我很寂寞 而且当时是深夜
It happened because I was bored one night, and it was late,
我在Facebook上搜索我的账号
and I was searching for my account on Facebook,
在搜索框里我打下了自己的名字
and I typed my name into the search bar and he came up
然后他就出现在屏幕里
and I saw him on the screen, and I was shocked that there was
我很震惊居然有一个人名字叫Kelly Hildebrandt
another person named Kelly Hildebrandt and that he was
还是个男的 于是我给他留了言
a boy. So I sent him a message.
她这样说 嗨 我们名字一样诶
She was like, "Hi, how's it going? We have the same name".
后来我就飞到了佛罗里达
and next thing I know I'm flying to Florida to meet
来见这个Kelly Hildebrandt
the other Kelly Hildebrandt.
当然我们还发现我们有许多相同点
Of course we found out we had a lot in common,
不仅仅是名字
other than just our names.
在我出来前我对牧师说
Before I came out I had told my pastor that
如果现实里的她与电话里的她一样
if she's the same person face to face that she is over the phone
那么她就是我一辈子的守护
that she's the girl for me.
最终女kelly正是男kelly的那个人
As it turned out Kelly WAS the right girl for Kelly.
因为他们现实里本应不会有任何联系
Having made sure they weren't directly related in any way,
于是他们在Facebook上结婚了
the two of them got married in a Facebook fever.
这种机会是极小极小的
The chances are one in a million's million.
两个人有同样的名字
The odds of someone having the exact same name, meeting,
相距1600英里远 最终见面
1600 miles apart and then just everything clicking and
可能性这么小的事居然发生了 太奇妙了
happening like it did, was just amazing.
两个kelly的奇妙缘分
The story of Kelly and Kelly's million-to-one chance meeting
在世界各地被报导
has been reported all over the world.
甚至加工成了深夜脱口秀的素材
And it even became fodder for the late night talk shows.
你火了你知道吗
You know you're famous when Conan O'Brien makes a joke
Conan O'Brien拿你的故事调侃呢
about your story.
是我们的故事
He told our story.
自从俩Kelly Hildebrandt比翼双飞
Kelly Hildebrandt marries Kelly Hildebrandt and just recently
潘棵前炎约旱拿字改成了章泽天
a hundred men changed their name to Meagan Fox.
对 在人人网上
Yeah! On, on Facebook
这是人类交流的
DR. MARK FEDERMAN: It's part
部分基本状况
of the fundamental human condition to connect.
有一句老话叫
There is that, almost trite cliche that says,
相逢何必曾相识 海角天涯若比邻
a stranger is a friend I haven't met yet. And in a world that is
真是绝句啊
in such proximity, it's a marvelous thought to hold.
我之前从未见过Kelly
KELLY : Before Facebook I would have never met Kelly,
我生命因为Facebook完全变了
so I think that it shifted the way my life was headed.
在这里我要感谢Facebook
KELLY : I am indebted to
给了我一个漂亮的妻子
Facebook for my beautiful wife, because if it
如果不是Facebook 我永远不会
wasn't for Facebook, I would never have met
遇见生命中另一个Kelly Hildebrandt
the other Kelly Hildebrandt.
有的人认为Facebook妙之处在于
Some people think one of Facebook's most inspired ideas
它的"情感状况"栏
is what's called "Relationship Status".
通过它能迅速筛选合适的人
It quickly signals who's available ... and who isn't.
有时候Facebook还会
And sometimes Facebook itself plays a leading role
起主导作用
in the drama.
马萨诸塞州的洛厄尔
Lowell, Massachusetts is the birthplace of
是美国工业革命的起源地
the American Industrial Revolution.
很久以前 洛厄尔靠纺织厂
Long ago, Lowell boomed with textile mills, which worked
加工南方来的棉花繁荣一时
the cotton from the South.
现在厂房都关闭了 最近几年
The mills are closed now, and in recent years
洛厄尔努力寻找自己的定位
Lowell has struggled to redefine itself.
我们在这里找到了Ken Savage
This is where we find Ken Savage, a man who has gone
他重新定位了自己 Facebook功不可没
through some redefinition of his own, thanks to Facebook.
我前妻最初用Facebook交友
My ex-wife used Facebook I think in the beginng to reach out to
但随后她就发现了它的魔力
friends. But as soon as she started to see the power of it,
她与一些前男友勾搭上了
she connected with some old boyfriends.
我们都能猜出后续剧情
We can all guess where this is heading.
是的 Ken的妻子欺骗他
Sure enough, Ken's wife cheated on him,
然后他撞破奸情
and he caught her doing it.
我认为是Facebook
I think Facebook brought upon the end of my marriage
加速了我婚姻的终结
much quicker than it would have been.
我们交流开始减少
The communication wasn't there. She took her focus away from me
她开始全身心投入Facebook
and put it onto Facebook.
她可能以为这一切都到头了
And I think it made her realize as well that this is over.
这些都不是她想要的 她能更轻易地
This is not what I want. I'm going to get what I want
从Facebook上得到满足
through Facebook much easier.
你可能听过这样的事 当然是真事
CLIVE THOMPSON: You will hear stories, and I'm sure they're true,
比如两个人在一个房间里
of couples who are like well, I'm in the room and I'd like to
一个人想对自己的配偶或伙伴唠嗑
talk to my spouse, my partner, but they're staring at
而另外一个却开始浏览Facebook
Facebook, you know.
因为那上面的社会热点连绵不绝
Because there's this very rich stream of social signals
引人入胜 让人流连往返
that are fascinating, and that person just can't pull away,
即使有人面对面坐在房里
even though there's someone sitting across the room
即使对方是自己的另一半
who's you know, supposed to be married to them.
Ken和他妻子离异了
Ken and his wife split up.
我向家人解释整个事件
I told family members what's going on. Why I moved out.
我告诉他们妻子瞒着我用Facebook
I said my wife is cheating on me using Facebook,
他们咯咯直笑 说你到底是干了神马
and they giggled and said, how do you do that?
我尝试解释这个问题
In attempting to answer the question,
Ken创建了一家自己的网站
Ken created a website of his own.
我的站点名为facebookcheating.Com
KEN SAVAGE: The website is called facebookcheating.Com .
这里有一个区域
There's a section here...
这是一个热门网站
This is one busy website,
最高一月点击量能达50000
up to fifty thousand hits in a typical month.
很明显 Ken并不是一个人在战斗
Clearly, Ken is not alone.
看这里有一篇关于类似于Facebook的社交媒体
KEN SAVAGE: And there's an article here about divorces from
导致离异的文章点击量正在上升
social media sites like Facebook are on the rise.
一家美国律师公司最近的一项研究显示
In a recent study conducted by a US law firm,
五分之一的婚外情都有Facebook在掺合
one in five marital affairs had a clear Facebook connection.
Ken已经挺过来了 婚姻的破裂和新家的结合
Ken has lived through it, a marriage lost and a new
不管你信不信 都因为Facebook
partner found - believe it or not - both on Facebook.
Ken创建的网站 现已开始盈利
And the final twist: Ken now makes money on a site
主题就是 Facebook上的那些欺骗
he created, all about Facebook cheating.
似乎所有的麻烦都来自Facebook的分享
With all this trouble caused by Facebook postings, surely
有Facebook让家庭更美好的例子吗
somewhere Facebook has changed family life for the better?
答案是 必须的
The answer is, of course, yes.
世界上有大约七亿人使用Facebook
With almost three quarters of a billion users in the world,
一些家庭便因为Facebook意外地
Facebook has helped to make some unexpected
有了联系
family connections.
在里贾纳社区的一栋房里
Inside this house in a quiet Regina neighbourhood
住着一个因为一个问题
lives someone who has struggled with a fundamental
纠结一生的人
question his whole life.
我从不曾感受父亲的慈爱
I never had a father's arm around my shoulders...
我没有爸爸
I just never had a father in my life.
这是Jim Toth 教育家 艺术家 环球旅行家
Meet Jim Toth. Educator, artist, world traveller,
还曾是魔术师
and one-time magician.
Jim的父母在他很小时就离异了
Jim's parents split up when he was very young,
他对父亲没有任何记忆
too young for him to remember his father.
当然他有继父 但他生父的身份
And while he did have a step-father, the identity of
被家庭当作秘密保守了几十年
his birth father stayed a family secret for decades.
我查了家谱 我去过Saskatchewan的档案馆
I did genealogy searches. I went to the archives in Saskatchewan.
我甚至去教堂 试图查出我的乳名
I even went to the Mormons, to try and find out something
仍一无所获
about my birth name. And I could get nothing.
你得找到位于顶端的搜索框
You have to go up to the search bar at the top...
当她外孙女Jeanelle介绍他看电脑上的一些新玩意儿时
That all changed the day his grand-daughter Jeanelle
一切都改变了
introduced him to something new on the computer.
试试搜搜Joseph
Maybe try Joseph...
她打字 然后Facebook回应
She typed in whatever she needed and up came Facebook.
我问她现在你能搜索相关人物吧
I said now you can search for people on this thing, can't you?
她说 能 那么好 我需要你帮我
She said, yes. So okay, I want you to help me.
好 试试Porkolab
Okay, try Porkolab.
突然跳出一个拇指大小的Porkolab
And all of a sudden up came the name Porkolab with a little
当时我震惊了 我从没想到
thumb sketch of a person. I was surprised. I didn't expect it.
这是我漫长寻找之旅的首次有积极回报
It was the first connection I have made that was positive,
一张照片就在我的眼前
right in front of my eyes.
我一眼就认出那是我的侄子
A picture, and in time I discovered that this was my
他是我同父异母兄弟的儿子
half-nephew, that I discovered, and he was the one that
他能让我们兄弟俩联系起来
connected me to my half-brother, just like that.
长达50多年的寻找
More than 50 years of searching
在Facebook上几分钟就搞定了
resolved in a few minutes on Facebook.
你好 Jim
hello jim,well,
该怎么说呢
I don't know quiet how to say this
你父亲是我祖父
but your father was my grandfather
那刻 那一行让我
That moment, that line gave me the connection that
五十多年来的寻找有了结果
for fifty years I was looking for.
你父亲是我的祖父 我写道
Your father is my grandfather. I made it.
50年的寻找 成功了
Fifty years of searching. I made it.
Facebook让我找到了家人
And Facebook was what enabled me to make that connection.
这些
CLIVE THOMPSON: So these
人类关系的突破
little brokerages of personal contact that could
过去很难发生甚至从没发生
never easily have happened, or never happened at all
现在就像家常便饭一样
in the past, you know, happen daily now.
这很喜人
And this is the delightful stuff.
这也是有些人们为什么即使会受伤
This is why people, sort of even if they're tortured by it
也会回到Facebook上来
keep returning to the Facebook well, is because
因为这些神奇的事仍在发生
these magical things still happen.
这个夏天Jim与他的新家人见面了
Jim met with his new family members this summer.
破镜能圆 脸谱之功
What was lost has been found, thanks to Facebook.
请看下一节 Facebook有可能
When we return: Is it possible that Facebook
成为逝去者的墓园吗
could make headstones, and cemeteries things of the past ?
社交媒体以各种方式把我们聚在一起
Social media brings us together in countless ways.
人生旅程之初
For people at the beginning of life's journey,
不可能想到世界上没有短信
it's impossible to imagine the world without texting and
没有推特和Facebook
Twitter and Facebook.
但在生命旅途到站前
For those near the journey's end, Facebook has raised some
我们已经在Facebook上留下了许多有趣的东西
interesting questions about what we leave behind.
这是伦敦维多利亚时代一大型墓园 Abney公墓
This is Abney Park, a huge Victorian cemetery in London.
数千人被埋葬在这里
There are thousands of people buried here.
但了解他们的生前经历是不可能的
But it's impossible to get a sense of who they were in life.
他们长得如何 他们的朋友是谁
What did they look like? Who were their friends?
他们爱过谁
Who did they love?
伦敦大学的Elaine Kaskett
Elaine Kaskett is a psychologist at the
是个心理学家
University of London. She has made a study of
她做了项人怎样悼念亡者的研究
how we mourn our loved ones.
在维多利亚时代人们建造大型墓园
They created big cemeteries like this in the Victorian period.
这反映了当时人类的社会状况
And it reflected the society in which people lived.
不仅在那个时代需要空间埋葬死者
Not just the needs of that society, who needed a place
在当代 也有同样的需要
to bury their dead, but the tastes of society.
这些冰冷的岩石刻着一些东西
This cold granite or stone engraved thing.
让它来代表你的一生如何
What is that of you? How is that a representation of the self?
当然不行 但Facebook可以
It's not. But a Facebook profile is.
人与死者交心的方法反映了
The way that people commune with the dead reflect the way
人们的生活方式 我们生活在一个网络社会时代
that people live. We live in a social networking age.
因此 这完全能够让人
It makes total sense, therefore, that people are going to
通过网络社会媒体和死者交流
commune with people who die via social networking media.
因为社会已经提供这种方法
Because that's the way our society is set up.
在这里亲友们
These are family and friends,
聚集在一起为Wilma Jones送终
gathered together to say goodbye to Wilma Jones.
我们将永远铭记她
She is going to be sadly missed by us all,
我们都爱她
because she was loved by us all.
Wilma是个Facebook用户
Wilma was a Facebook user.
2010年她死后 她的页面还保留着
After she died in 2010, her page stayed up, and
人们开始在她页面上留言 所有人都能看到
people started leaving posts on her wall for everyone to see.
Wilma我爱你
I love you Wilma
我知道天堂已经接纳了你
and I know that heaven has accepted you with open arms.
替我给那里所有人一个大大的拥抱和亲吻
Since you are there,give all the family a big hug and kiss for me.
如果你是一个Facebook控
If you're a really avid Facebook user,
你发表很多状态 有很多朋友
and you post lots of things, and you have lots of friends
与很多人交流 相册里有许多评论
and lots of conversations and lots of comments on photographs
诸如此类
and all these kinds of things, it's an incredibly rich
那将是你及其丰富和详实的人生写照
and complex record of who you were.
不仅仅作为你个人
Not just who you were as an individual, but who you were
还作为各种人际关系中的你
in the context of all your relationships, including your
包括你离开人世后
relationships with the people that you leave behind
与在世者的联系
when you die.
Jessie 说点什么
Jessie, okay?
"她"就是一种爱 Wilma留给我们的爱
She was just like love, that's what Wilma was, love.
这就是我想说的
And that's all. That's all I'd like to say.
谢谢你Jessie
Thank you Jessie.
我认为"她"是一份生命的遗物
I think she's a testament to what we need to remember -
我们都需铭记"她"
what life is about. MOURNERS: Amen.
对很多人来说在Facebook上与人交流
For a lot of people it seems like continuing to communicate
似乎感觉是最真实最交心的方式
with somebody on Facebook feels like the most real,
这种方式能让他们真正地向人倾诉
the most connected kind of way that they can really speak to
并相信能真正被人倾听
somebody and have faith that they're being heard.
这是很强大的力量
And that's quite powerful stuff.
姨妈 我感到很宽慰和惊喜
hey auntie.I find it so weird and yet so comforting
每当我想和你说话的时候都可以上Facebook
that whenever I want to talk with you i come on fb
然后给你留言
and write on your wall.
每当我敲下确定键 我确信
It's almost as if when i press enter i can be certain
我的短信能直达天堂
that my message is being sent staight to heaven.
于是有人会怀疑在未来
ELAINE KASKETT: So one does wonder whether in the future,
是否仍会有这样的地方
one wonders whether there will still be places like this
满是和我周围一样的墓碑
full of grave markers like those that surround me here.
因为现在看起来似乎没有这个必要了
Because when it's hard to imagine the need for it
现在死者的代理能如此丰富
when there's such a vivid representation of the person
在手机或电脑屏幕前
that you lost right there in front of you on your
它让你欢喜让你忧
computer screen or on your phone screen.
阿门 感谢每一个人
AMEN. Thank you everybody.
我们年轻的时候 总是牛逼哄哄
When we're young, we tend to think of ourselves as immortal.
管谁他会在不经意间看到这些照片呢
What does it matter who sees pictures of us
看去呗
in unguarded moments... having fun...
脑残?管他三七二十一呢
speaking our minds? Who cares?
不过 Ray Lam就是这么做的 还有Nathalie Blanchard
Well, Ray Lam does... so does Nathalie Blanchard
还有Paul Chambers,Cameron Reilly和众议员Weiner
and Paul Chambers and Cameron Reilly and Anthony Weiner...
还有温哥华那千多个骚乱者
and any one of thousands of rioters in Vancouver.
总是总是在继续  遍布全球
And on and on it goes... all over the world....
人们身败名裂
peoples' reputations being undone
只因为社交媒体的使用
by the use of social media.
如果你不想成为公众人物
If you're not prepared to go to the middle
或者不愿提着大喇叭
of your city centre, and get a loud-hailer
用它大声喊着自己的私人信息
and shout out your personal information through that,
那么还是上点心吧
don't put it on the Internet.
任何你不想公布的东西
Anything which you don't want becoming public
都不要发布到网络上
you should never post on the Internet
因为实际上你是在信任
because you're effectively putting your trust
一家公司能保守你的个人隐私信息
in a company to keep your personal information secret.
而那并不是他们的商业模式
And that isn't always their business model.
不管facebook的商业模式是什么
whatever facebook business model is
它正在运行
it's working.
它决定于剩下的人最终怎么改编
And it's up to the rest of us to figure out how to adapt.
数字化生活 一部分线上和一部分线下
Living digitally, living partly on-line and partly off-line
看似独立，却会互相影响
is always going to have this push and pull of weird tensions.
最终将会出现一种比起当下的Facebook
So it may be that we wind up in an even stickier wicket
更有弹性的东西
than we're in right now with Facebook.
下一代社交媒体将会有所改进
The next generation of social media will be upon us
或许在遥远的未来
before we know it. And one far-off day,
Facebook和推特将和电报一样被推崇
Facebook and Twitter will seem as quaint as the telegraph.
并不是说推特和Facebook会改变社会
It's not that Facebook or Twitter will change society.
他们是历史巨轮的润滑剂
They're merely a grease for the wheels.
它们促进了现今的改变
They help move along a change that we're passing through now
如果被充分认识 还会促进下一个
that will yet take another hundred fifty or so years
世纪的改变 一旦达到另一种极致
to be fully realized. Once we come out the other end,
那将是一个完全完全不同的世界
it will be a very, very different world.